Hamas says it would allegedly release all Israeli hostages in exchange for Palestinians
imprisoned by Israel.
Even before October 7, Israel was holding more than a thousand Palestinian detainees
without charge.
Just a few days ago, Israel detained thousands of Gazans who are lawfully working in Israel
with work permits.
According to Gisha, an Israeli NGO whose goal is to protect the freedom of movement of Palestinians,
the arrests were made without cause.
So now, thousands of Palestinians are incarcerated in Israel without charge or trial.
As things tense up, legal advocates and human rights activists are showing that there are
a lot of Palestinian hostages on the other side.
At the end of June 2023, the Israel Prison Service was holding 1,117 Palestinians in administrative
detention.
Beth Selem, an Israeli human rights organization, explains what administrative detention means.
It means incarceration without trial or charge, alleging that a person plans to commit a future
offense.
That person faces unknown allegations with no way to disprove them.
Under Israeli law, administrative detention can be extended every six months, without limit.
Extensions are reviewed by an Israeli military court, behind closed doors, based on secret
material that is not even disclosed to the defense attorney.
One former judge even admitted in an interview, quote, all my information comes through the
Israeli general security service agents.
I didn't doubt what they said.
About 100 percent of all military court cases in the West Bank end in conviction.
Palestinian Prisoner Society reports that 95 percent of Palestinian detainees have suffered
from torture in prison.
We would hear screams from other cells and smell tear gas, but we couldn't tell what was
happening.
Some prisoners would tell us about beatings by Israeli forces.
Their hands were broken, and heads and backs were injured.
This is happening to children, too.
Hundreds of Palestinian prisoners are below the age of 18.
In a report from July, kids said that they were violated sexually and put in cages.
For scale, the number of Palestinian children in Israeli detention in a single year exceeds
the total number of people held by the U.S. in Guantanamo since 2002.
Palestinians in Israeli prisons are systematically denied family visits and phone calls.
There's also overcrowding, and just last week, Israeli parliament approved measures to make
the living spaces even smaller.
According to Military Court Watch, Israel has detained about 800,000 Palestinians since
1967.
But that number is actually just a rough estimate, because actually, Israel doesn't publish clear
or accurate information about Palestinians in custody.
One thing we do know, in the last couple of weeks, Israel has doubled its number of Palestinian
prisoners, growing to about 10,000.
Al Jazeera reports that since October 7, Israel has arrested 4,000 laborers from Gaza and more
than 1,000 people in the West Bank.
May all civilian hostages on both sides be released.